<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Tom Wilson</title>
  <subtitle></subtitle>
  <link href="https://www.tomwilson.nz/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://www.tomwilson.nz/"/>
  
    <updated>2025-11-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
  
  <id>https://www.tomwilson.nz</id>
  <author>
    <name>Tom Wilson</name>
    <email>tommo.wilson@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  
    
    <entry>
      <title>How to remain connected when you&#39;re triggered in a partnership</title>
      <link href="https://www.tomwilson.nz/posts/remaining-connected-triggered/"/>
      <updated>2025-10-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <id>https://www.tomwilson.nz/posts/remaining-connected-triggered/</id>
      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
      <p>One of the biggest struggles I see with couples is that they find themselves in a state where they are &quot;triggered&quot; and then they are no-longer operating from their full-self that can see the bigger picture.</p>
<p>Instead, defense-mechanisms come online to run the conversation. The whole paradigm of the relationship changes in that moment. It's no longer team-work, it's you-vs-me. It's war. It's attack and defense.</p>
<p>From this place, they no longer have access to their full set of resources. They are limited to strategies that help them to stay safe. They may shut down, hide, attack or exhibit a range of behaviours that are quite unhelpful to a loving connected relationship.</p>
<p>People say things like &quot;everything is great when things are going well, but once there is some conflict, it escalates into a fight. From there, it doesn't seem like there's much I can do to bring things back&quot;</p>
<p>What I would like to share here is some thoughts about how to navigate this situation differently so that you don't find yourself stuck in way of being that ultimately erodes trust and damages relationships.</p>
<p>Instead you can develop the skills and awareness to navigate conflict in a way that can maintain connection with the other person while still being able to work through the difficulty.</p>
<h2>Relationship Agreement</h2>
<p>Lets start really big picture. It is really important to have conversations about your relationship when you're in a relationship.</p>
<p>One of those important conversations is about HOW we're going to relate to each other.</p>
<p>Within that conversation it is useful to cover some things that are absolute no-go's. Things that if they happen are huge red-flags.</p>
<p>For example: A common thing I've witnessed is that in the heat of the moment, some people threaten to leave the relationship.</p>
<p>A rule that I have in my relationship that I developed early on with Juliana, is that threatening to leave is absolutely forbidden. Not because it's about control and trying to stop her or me from leaving. But rather that it's about safety. I know that if there is a threat lurking in the background that if things are getting difficult between us then there's a risk that she will leave, it adds a whole other layer of pressure to the relationship that undermines the integrity of it.</p>
<p>So having this agreement in place means that we avoid these types of interactions and it provides the stability and safety that the other person is going to be there and stay in connection no matter what happens. This in itself is a huge plus for navigating difficulties.</p>
<h2>Understand your nervous system / and each others</h2>
<p>The behaviour of shutting down or defending or hiding etc is a nervous system response. It's normal, it's natural, it's healthy.</p>
<p>That said, it can also have unhealthy effects.</p>
<p>This is a fact of being a human. We have nervous systems and we can experience all of those feelings and behaviours.</p>
<p>It is absolutely imperative that you develop awareness of your nervous system response if you are to be in relationship with people.  If you don't know the automatic knee-jerk responses that you are likely to have then you will be stuck with them and not even know why it's happening.</p>
<p>With awareness however, you can gain understanding. You can begin to watch it in real-time and this gives you opportunity to step in and change it.</p>
<p>Instead of going direct to attack mode or hiding mode, you will instead notice the impulse to pull away or the impulse to use threatening language.</p>
<p>From this place, you actually have a choice. You can continue on down that path, or you can pull back, name what is happening for you and choose to remain in connection.</p>
<p>Also, from this moment, you actually have to opportunity to choose to remain in connection with your partner and identify the pattern that is happening. If you understand your own nervous system and your partners, you can clearly articulate what is happening so that it becomes &quot;us-vs-the pattern&quot; instead of me-vs-you.</p>
<p>Once you see it, you can discuss it and it no longer runs the show anymore.</p>
<h2>Courageously bring your vulnerability</h2>
<p>Deep down in us humans it is soft and vulnerable. At the heart of every conflict there is usually a question which is something like &quot;do you still care about me?&quot;</p>
<p>We all interpret the world in different ways. If you do something, it might have a different meaning for me. That can cause me to question if you still care about me.</p>
<p>The quicker that I can courageously go to the heart of my pain and share it, the faster a conflict will diffuse.</p>
<p>If I can honestly search inside and look for the part of me that I'm trying to protect and instead of doing that, bring it forward, it completely changes things.</p>
<p>Something like... &quot;Hey, I'm noticing that I feel scared. I'm afraid that you're not attracted me anymore and I'm afraid of what that means for us going forwards.&quot;</p>
<p>Or... &quot;Hey, I feel angry and I'm telling myself the story that you don't care about me anymore because you did XYZ&quot;</p>
<p>etc.</p>
<p>Get to the feeling you don't want to share.
The sadness. The fear. The Anger. The softness. The vulnerability.</p>
<h2>Bring Curiosity Online</h2>
<p>Curiosity is an actual super-power. If you can manage to find curiosity in a moment of difficulty it will completely change things.</p>
<p>I mean genuine curiosity.</p>
<p>Curiosity that wonders what it might be like to see the world through anothers eyes.</p>
<p>Not curiosity to gain additional ammunition. Curiosity that helps you understand. Deeply. The other person.</p>
<p>Bring it in, next time you feel challenged. In fact, bring it in when you're not feeling challenged and it will make the challenging times easier because you will actually have deeper understanding of one-another and you will have built the muscle of empathy with each other previously.</p>
<p>I hope you give these ideas some consideration. They make a huge difference if you're struggling with conflict that accelerates quickly.</p>

    ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
  
    
    <entry>
      <title>What Happens When You Stop Treating Your Body Like a Machine</title>
      <link href="https://www.tomwilson.nz/posts/shoulder-pain-self-image/"/>
      <updated>2025-10-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <id>https://www.tomwilson.nz/posts/shoulder-pain-self-image/</id>
      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
      <p>A man told me the other day that his shoulder hurt. This is not an uncommon experience for me. I work with people 1:1 to help them resolve issues like this.</p>
<p>What I realised as I spoke to him is that he was viewing his body in a particular way. He was viewing it as separate parts. This part is my shoulder. This part is my back. This part is my knee. Etc.</p>
<p>Again, this is not uncommon. We hear songs early in life, like <em>&quot;head, shoulders knees and toes&quot;</em>. We need to be able to label and box different bits of ourselves for our language and shared understanding.</p>
<p>But this way of seeing yourself can set you up for pain and difficulty in your movement. It's a perception problem and I believe it's at the root of a lot of painful experiences people have in their body's.</p>
<p>To change this situation, there are different ways of seeing yourself which mean that our movement and sense of being alive is more joyful and pleasure-rich.</p>
<h2>Perception influences reality</h2>
<p>Our thinking - the way we imagine ourselves to be - has an influence on the way we function.</p>
<p>Imagine you're a robot and you're lifting your arm towards the ceiling. Notice how that feels.</p>
<p>Now let go of the robot idea and imagine your lungs are filling with warm air. And because warmer air rises, it begins to flow up through your shoulder and your arm and your arm begins to float upward. The higher it rises, the more the warm air gently fills your arm and hand and encourages it to rise all on it's own, up towards the ceiling.</p>
<p>Notice that those 2 experiences are different? Which image requires less effort to lift your arm?</p>
<p>Nothing changed about your physical arm. Your perception of your arm and it's movement changed. This influenced the muscular contraction patterns that guided your arm to move in that way.</p>
<p>Your perception or self-image influenced your physical reality.</p>
<p>If we go back to this man and his perception of himself as individual parts it creates a certain lived experience of movement and sensation.</p>
<p>In this particular way of viewing himself, he was creating pain for himself.</p>
<p>And if you're wondering - yes I AM saying that the way he view's himself creates the pain he's in.</p>
<p>But what could he have done differently? Well, what's the opposite of differentiated parts?</p>
<p>Integrated whole.</p>
<p>That's right, when I can see myself as a whole integrated being (the whole integrated being that I ACTUALLY AM), my life gets a heck of a lot easier. My movement becomes more fluid. I get more coordinated and the quality of my movement improves. I feel more powerful, connected and joyful about life too.</p>
<p>But this isn't just a simple mind trick like the robot vs. warm air.</p>
<p>Changing ones self-image takes practice. Because practice gives you the lived experience that you actually ARE a whole integrated being.</p>
<p>I remember the first time I saw a real live heart. It had just been taken out of a goat that had been alive moments earlier. It was still &quot;beating&quot;. Though beating is a terrible description.</p>
<p>Rippling with waves is a more apt description. I realised that I had been imagining a heart based on a more mechanical image. I was thinking it was more like a pump. Something that goes thump, thump, thump, thump etc etc.</p>
<p>But seeing the reality of a real live, organic heart completely changed my image. Hearts are beautiful. They produce waves of movement.  They're fluid and smooth and rippling. They are more akin to a musical instrument creating pulsing rhythmic sound.</p>
<p>These are the types of experience that practice can give you. They can help to update your image of what your body actually is. An organic, pulsing, living, fluid, rippling organism that is dynamic and changing and ALIVE.</p>
<p>If you'd like to learn the type of practice that can help you see yourself in this more accurate and empowering way, PM me.</p>

    ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
  
    
    <entry>
      <title>The Art of Unraveling - How to Work with Life’s Knots Instead of Fighting Them</title>
      <link href="https://www.tomwilson.nz/posts/why-tugging-harder-tightens-the-knot/"/>
      <updated>2025-10-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <id>https://www.tomwilson.nz/posts/why-tugging-harder-tightens-the-knot/</id>
      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
      <p>Do you ever get stuck in the same pattern, repeating yourself over and over, but not being able to escape from it? Maybe it's the same fight you get into with your partner. Maybe it's feelings of anxiety. Maybe it's a sore neck.</p>
<p>I would like to share a metaphor which I believe can shed some light on this cycle.</p>
<p>My work is about process. I see a vast woven tapestry with thousands of interconnected threads.</p>
<p>My first step is to in the beauty and complexity of the whole tapestry. Then I get a sense, somewhere in my gut, that there are knotted areas. Places that, if untangled, could make the whole tapestry even more harmonious and beautiful.</p>
<p>I don't know how to untangle them, but I can feel there's some kind of constriction. Only through curious and specific observation does it become obvious how the knot wants to &quot;unravel&quot;.</p>
<p>If I tug too tightly on one thread, it tightens the whole knot again. It's precision work.</p>
<p>If I rush, I lose the thread. The knot remains.</p>
<p>If I forget the whole while looking at the part, I lose the meaning and cannot progress.</p>
<p>It's a delicate art that honours the process.</p>
<p>How I move through is as important as the outcome itself.</p>
<p>But when the knot is un-done, the whole tapestry takes on a different look. It's more harmonious. More connected. It knows itself better.</p>
<p>This is what practices like Feldenkrais or relational awareness work are about — learning to move through life with sensitivity to process, rather than control of outcome.</p>
<p>Practices that honour the process as much as the outcome. Practices that honour relationship and connection.</p>
<p>If you give yourself the gift of practicing something over and over again with your focus on the <strong>quality</strong> of how you do it, as opposed to &quot;getting the outcome you want&quot;. It will change your life.</p>
<p>Forever.</p>
<p>I work in seemingly unrelated fields. I help people with chronic pain and people who want to improve their relationship with their loved ones.</p>
<p>But underneath the hood, it's the same process.</p>
<p>We look at the tapestry, we work with the knots we find and we practice moving with presence, relationship, ease and honesty.</p>
<p>Perhaps you've noticed these knots in yourself before. A stumbling block in your intimate relationship? A parenting struggle? A sore back that just won't respond to what you're doing.</p>
<p>You probably also have a default response to these knots. Maybe you try to stretch your back. Maybe you feel yourself get angry with your kid and then berate yourself later for being too aggressive? Maybe you close off to your partner and pull back until it's passed over.</p>
<p>What if there was a different way of approaching these knots? What if instead of tugging on them desperately, trying to make them disappear, you looked at them patiently and gently. What if your intent was to understand? What if you committed to honouring the WAY that you work with your knot?</p>
<p>You know those values that you admire the most about yourself when things are going well? Maybe it's care, or love, or nurturing. Curiosity, respect or humour.</p>
<p>What might it be like to bring some of these values - your highest values - to the way that you work with your knots?</p>
<p>Next time you notice a knot — in your body, or your relationship — pause. Breathe. Feel it. Then ask yourself: what would it look like to meet this knot while honouring the process?</p>
<p>I’d love to hear what you discover.</p>

    ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
  
    
    <entry>
      <title>Gentle Honesty - The Art of Speaking Truth Without Breaking Connection</title>
      <link href="https://www.tomwilson.nz/posts/gentle-honesty-speaking-truth-without-breaking-connection/"/>
      <updated>2025-10-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <id>https://www.tomwilson.nz/posts/gentle-honesty-speaking-truth-without-breaking-connection/</id>
      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
      <p>You want to be honest. You really do.
You value openness, depth, and truth.</p>
<p>But when it comes to saying what’s <em>really</em> going on for you, your throat tightens, your chest contracts, and suddenly… the words don’t come out right.<br>
You’re not alone in that.</p>
<p>If you notice your body reacting as you read — a little tightness, a sigh, a bit of sadness — that’s okay. It’s just your system recognizing something true.</p>
<p>Maybe you feel like your words would be too much. Maybe you fear the other person will take it the wrong way. Maybe it's difficult to get the words out in a way that matches what you're actually feeling - this used to be a big one for me!</p>
<p>Would you like to be able to have open and honest conversations with more ease? What if you could say what you felt in such a way that you could be proud of your clarity and transparency.</p>
<h2>Cultural Differences in Communication</h2>
<p>My partner is Argentinian and I am from New Zealand. Culturally we are opposites when it comes to communication.</p>
<p>New Zealanders are generally indirect. We do things we think are &quot;polite&quot;. We say sorry even when it's not our fault and we say thankyou until it gets awkward. We use lots of words like &quot;perhaps&quot; and &quot;maybe&quot; that dampen the impact (and therefore the clarity) of what we're about to say. If someone messages us with a request and our answer is no, we just say nothing rather than risk disappointing someone.</p>
<p>Ughh — it feels cringy to even write that. But it’s true. It’s where I came from, and it shaped how I learned to protect myself.</p>
<p>Argentinians on the other hand are direct and fiery. They are not afraid of conflict and they say EXACTLY what's on their minds. My eyes must have been the size of dinner plates the first time I went to Argentina, sitting down to a family dinner. It felt like a full on war was breaking out around me - but to them it was normal.</p>
<p>Needless to say, this difference in expectations and behaviours came up a lot during the early stages of our relationship.</p>
<p>The pattern goes something like this...</p>
<h2>How Our Protection Patterns Collide</h2>
<p>She says something direct and truthful. I interpret it as attack. My defense mechanism of silence and retreat comes online. She gets frustrated because I'm not being clear about what I want. I get more and more withdrawn. She gets more and more direct and frustrated.</p>
<p>OUCH</p>
<p>That was our cycle for a long time. And it hurt — not because we didn’t love each other, but because we were both protecting ourselves in the only ways we knew how.</p>
<p>Your pattern may be different. Different histories, expectations, traumas, cultural norms, gender norms, etc.</p>
<p>These things all impact on couples' abilities to have open, honest, connected and productive conversations.</p>
<p>When these layers combine — culture, upbringing, nervous system wiring — even love can’t override our instinct to protect ourselves.</p>
<p>So what can we do when honesty feels risky — when we <em>want</em> to be open, but our body says no?</p>
<h2>When Safety Disappears, So Does Honesty</h2>
<p>Have you ever been in an environment where it was easy to speak your truth. It flowed out of you and felt effortless. My guess is that you probably felt safe to do so.</p>
<p>Difficulty expressing honestly is directly related to how safe you feel. Those compensations that dilute your meaning only exist because, somewhere deep down, it doesn’t feel safe to do otherwise.</p>
<p>Safety is foundational. Our nervous systems have a neuroception of safety. That is - they're always scanning the environment in the background of our awareness to sense how safe or dangerous it is. When we judge unconsciously that it's safe, we can be in a more socially engaged mode of being.</p>
<p>In this space of safety, truth speaking is natural.</p>
<p>So if you have a background sense in your relationship that it's unsafe to speak the truth. You're going to have to find ways to support yourself to feel safe.</p>
<h2>How to Re-Establish Safety</h2>
<p>Here are some ways I know of that might help re-establish safety - so you can relax.</p>
<h3>Practical Ways to Create Safety Together</h3>
<ul>
<li>Naming the fear to your partner - &quot;I'm feeling afraid to speak the truth right now.&quot; This is a micro act of speaking what's true. It reveals vulnerability. It breaks the spell.</li>
<li>Asking for support - &quot;What would help me feel more safe is if you...&quot;
<ul>
<li>&quot;...told me you love me.&quot;</li>
<li>&quot;...let me finish speaking before you speak.&quot;</li>
<li>&quot;...put your hand on me.&quot;</li>
<li>&quot;...shared how you're feeling.&quot;</li>
<li>&quot;...give me your full attention for a few minutes&quot;</li>
<li>&quot;...just share the space with me for a few minutes without any pressure to talk.&quot;</li>
<li>&quot;...reassure me that we're on the same team, no matter what&quot;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Identifying the ways in which your own survival mechanisms are operating right now - &quot;I'm finding it difficult to breathe. I'm feeling really shut down. I'm feeling anxious. I have a desire to run away. I have a desire to be very close to you and I'm afraid that I might be too much and scare you away.&quot;</li>
<li>Talk about how it's hard for you to tell the truth sometimes with your partner - probably best done when there is nothing pressing. Engage with curiosity.</li>
<li>Providing you've had this conversation in the past, let your partner know that it's happening for you again.</li>
<li>Have a practice of doing regular check-ins with each other. Get used to speaking vulnerabilities with each other with low stakes. As confidence builds, take bigger risks.</li>
<li>Learn about Nonviolent Communication (NVC). It’s a beautiful framework for expressing what’s alive inside you — your feelings, needs, and requests — in a way that creates understanding rather than distance.</li>
</ul>
<p>I know - if you felt your chest tighten just reading the above, it's okay. These things can be scary. But just know you don't have to do it perfectly and you don't have to do it all now.</p>
<p>Small truths spoken with warmth have power beyond what you might imagine right now.</p>
<h2>Building the Muscles of Emotional Honesty</h2>
<p>Here's some things I notice about the suggestions I gave.</p>
<ol>
<li>There is an element of risk and vulnerability involved. It requires being able to summon the courage to take small risks and see how they are received. Paradoxically, taking this leap can lead to feeling safer.</li>
<li>They invite a sense of teamwork into your partnership (which can be one of the first things to leave when it doesn't feel safe).</li>
<li>There's also an aspect of skill building. What is your emotional intelligence like? Your somatic intelligence? How familiar are you with what is happening internally? These skills also impact your ability to express truly what is going on.</li>
</ol>
<h2>Try This Today</h2>
<p>Think of one small truth you’ve been holding back — something gentle but real.<br>
Say it aloud to yourself first.<br>
Notice what happens in your body.<br>
If it feels okay, share it with someone you trust.<br>
Every small act of honesty builds the muscle for the next.</p>
<h2>The Bigger Picture</h2>
<p>I encourage you to give these suggestions a try. Investing in the skillset of emotional honesty is something that pays back BIG-TIME.</p>
<p>I have a relationship in which I can share anything about what's going on within me. That level of trust is a huge asset in my life. I know I have someone next to me who's got my back. Someone who, if things get tough, can be there to listen to me. I know that no matter what is going on, she will be there to support. And I know she feels the same way about me.</p>
<p>That's teamwork.</p>
<p>Working as a team to create an environment where emotional honesty is the norm is something that will gradually sculpt your life in ways you cannot predict.</p>
<p>Over time, that honesty fills your cup until it overflows — and what spills out is warmth, connection, and quiet confidence that touches every other part of your life.</p>
<p>That’s the kind of love that doesn’t just stay between two people — it ripples outward.</p>

    ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
  
    
    <entry>
      <title>Why Your Body Wont Let Go And What You Can Do About It</title>
      <link href="https://www.tomwilson.nz/posts/why-your-body-wont-let-go/"/>
      <updated>2025-11-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <id>https://www.tomwilson.nz/posts/why-your-body-wont-let-go/</id>
      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
      <p>Do you ever feel like no matter how much you rest, your body never really lets go?</p>
<p>Maybe you stretch, meditate, or get massages, but the relief is fleeting. You feel like you <em>should</em> be able to release tension easily… yet somehow, your body doesn’t cooperate.</p>
<p>If this feels familiar, you’re not broken. It’s actually very human: your brain and nervous system are doing exactly what they’re designed to do. The very systems that keep you alive and safe are also the ones that maintain tension — even when it feels frustrating.</p>
<p>You want your body to relax, yet your nervous system keeps you alert. You want ease, yet your system insists on readiness. This paradox is normal — it’s your biology speaking.</p>
<h2>Why Pushing Harder Backfires</h2>
<p>Many people I see live in a state of constant pushing, trying, and fighting their way forward. Maybe it’s about feeling safe, maybe it’s cultural conditioning — the belief that if you don’t know how to do something perfectly, the answer is to push harder.</p>
<p>I used to be this way too. I trained a lot — until my background tension got so high that I literally couldn’t walk properly anymore. I know how it feels to be trapped in a body that doesn’t let go.</p>
<h2>Tension isn't your fault</h2>
<p>Here’s something to consider: your tension isn’t a personal failing. It’s a systemic response. Your muscles aren’t the problem — they’re just following instructions from your nervous system.</p>
<p>If you have tight neck or back muscles - they are just a symptom. They're not the cause.</p>
<p>The good news about this is that brains are plastic. They can change. And they can change quickly if the conditions are right. It's possible for you to learn how to have a body that feels comfortable and at ease. You can live in a way that it feels simple and enjoyable to just sit there and breathe naturally deep breaths. You can walk up stairs or sleep in your bed in a way that feels like your body is happy to do so.</p>
<p>Maybe even just hearing that is a relief. And I know it's true because I've felt it myself. And I've seen it happen for many of my clients.</p>
<p>The truth is, your brain can feel safe and content in the world, just the way you are right now.</p>
<p>The way to get there requires some learning and some practice.</p>
<p>To give you some idea of what that journey looks like. I'll give you a couple of the key ideas that it's necessary to embody in order to feel this level of ease and freedom.</p>
<h2>Ease is a practice</h2>
<p>In strength training and pretty much any sort of athletic endeavour, the mantra is that you need to continually push your limits. If you did 30 pushups this week, you need to do 32 or 35 next week. In this way, you build up your capacity to do work.</p>
<p>But have you ever tried to &quot;push the limits&quot; of your ease?</p>
<p>What if you had to do reps of a movement, but each time aiming to make it simpler and gentler and easier than the last.</p>
<p>Our nervous systems are built upon patterns or habits. If we practice a particular pattern, it gets easier to us.</p>
<p>If we practice ease, it starts to feel more natural and it becomes our normal.</p>
<p>Just like it’s natural to push harder when you want to improve strength, it’s also natural to resist letting go of tension when your nervous system feels it needs you alert.</p>
<p>The paradox is that the very practice of easing can initially feel like “not doing enough,” even though it’s exactly what your system needs.</p>
<h2>Your Body and Mind are A System</h2>
<p>Have you noticed how it's difficult to tell if the tension you feel is physical or emotional?</p>
<p>Maybe sometimes it feels more physical, maybe others more emotional. Maybe if you didn't sleep well, your body will feel tighter the next day.</p>
<p>This isn't some weird mistake. Since the tension in your body is governed at a central location (ie: your brain) it makes sense that everything affects it.</p>
<p>The truth is, your emotions, your thoughts, your relationships, your food intake, your injuries, your traumas, etc all influence the state of your nervous system.</p>
<p>And when you influence your nervous system in a way that supports it in coming back to calm, you will feel it in all of these domains too.</p>
<p>If you improve the ease of your movement, your muscle tone will soften, your thoughts will become more coherent, your emotional state will feel more positive and on and on...</p>
<h2>A Simple Practice to Invite Deeper Relaxation</h2>
<p>Here's something to try today to give you a sense of what it's like to relax at a nervous system level.</p>
<p>You might notice some resistance at first — your body may “want” to tighten again, or your mind might tell you this isn’t enough. That’s normal. The paradox is: by <em>not pushing</em>, you’re actually training your nervous system more deeply than by forcing movement.</p>
<ol>
<li>Lie down and get as comfortable as you can. Use pillows or towels folded underneath your head and anywhere else you feel needs it. Take this step seriously, it makes a difference. With this type of support you're giving your nervous system cues that it is safe and it's okay to let go.</li>
<li>Firstly, pay attention to your breath so you have a baseline for comparison. How fast is it going? Which parts of your body move when you breathe and which parts stay still? How deep does your breathing feel?</li>
<li>Now put one hand on your belly and one hand on your chest.</li>
<li>Take a breath in and hold it. Don't inhale as deep as you can. Maybe 80% of your capacity. Nothing that feels too stressful. Now with a held breath, begin to move your torso in such a way that you move the air up into your chest. Your chest should expand and push your hand out. At the same time, your belly will pull in and your hand will move closer to your spine. Then reverse it so that you push your belly out and your chest goes in. Continue to do this movement alternating with your belly and chest going in opposite directions. Only do this a few times before exhaling again. You don't need to push the limits. Just take it easy.</li>
<li>Repeat this for several cycles - each time trying to do the movement with more ease and less effort. Don't push your limits of how far you can move your chest or belly. Just keep it simple and don't do your best!</li>
<li>Now just allow yourself to breathe naturally.</li>
<li>Pay attention to the way your breath feels now. How fast is it going? Which parts of your body move when you breathe and which parts stay still? How deep does your breathing feel?</li>
</ol>
<p>If you are feeling more relaxed and at ease, even just a little bit - you can see how just a few minutes of &quot;practicing ease&quot; can have positive effects on your nervous system.</p>
<p>Remember how I said this was systemic. Notice if there's anything different about how you feel in general. Emotiions. Thoughts. Feelings. Physical comfort.</p>
<h2>Feeling Good is Possible</h2>
<p>As a former &quot;tension-addict&quot;, I can attest to the fact that it's possible to change your patterns.</p>
<p>I used to feel a lot of chronic pain and chronic tension. I know that with some work you can reverse this situation and feel better in your body than ever before.</p>
<p>The encouraging thing is that it doesn't come from working harder. It comes from learning to work in harmony with your nervous system.</p>
<p>You can use curiosity and gentleness to develop a sweet and loving relationship with your body and it will have profound effects on your entire system.</p>
<p>Isn't it a relief to know that progress can come from doing less?</p>

    ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
  
    
    <entry>
      <title>Boundaries Without Walls - How to Protect Yourself and Stay Connected</title>
      <link href="https://www.tomwilson.nz/posts/boundaries-without-walls-protect-yourself-stay-connected/"/>
      <updated>2025-11-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <id>https://www.tomwilson.nz/posts/boundaries-without-walls-protect-yourself-stay-connected/</id>
      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
      <p>Do you ever feel overstimulated around people but you don't want to push them away? You deeply value human connection, yet it all just feels too much sometimes. Maybe you're not sure what to do with these seemingly opposing feelings so you either run away and hide or you suck it up and push through, but then feel terrible later.</p>
<p>It’s confusing, right? You want to be kind. You want to belong. But you also crave quiet, or space, or simply a moment to breathe. You start wondering if something’s wrong with you for needing that.</p>
<p>If that’s you, you’re not alone. Many sensitive people find that the very closeness they crave can also become overwhelming.</p>
<h2>The Common Advice About Boundaries (and Why It Can Feel Harsh)</h2>
<p>You've probably heard things like...</p>
<ul>
<li>“Boundaries are self-care.”</li>
<li>“You teach people how to treat you.”</li>
<li>“Protect your peace.”</li>
<li>“If someone crosses your boundary, cut them off.”</li>
</ul>
<p>But perhaps you sense that this angle has an edge of harshness? It aims to create safety through separation. The hidden implication is that connection is dangerous.</p>
<h2>What If Connection and Self-Care Don’t Have to Compete?</h2>
<p>I would like to share an alternative approach which honours both the need for connection and the desire for self care - without making either wrong.</p>
<p>Both matter deeply — and you can learn to meet them at the same time.</p>
<h2>When Boundaries Meet Real Life (and Real People)</h2>
<p>I live with 3 children and my partner. In this situation I have learned the necessity of using boundaries, but I don't have the &quot;luxury&quot; of cutting someone off if they cross them. I also don't want to. I love my children dearly and it's important that they feel attached and secure in their lives.</p>
<p>Sometimes though, my children are wild beasts. Raucous, noisy, unpredictable. At times it feels like every noise my daughter makes is like a knife stabbing into my brain.</p>
<p>It’s hard because the very person I love most is also the source of my overload.</p>
<p>Sometimes when I ask nicely for her to stop or quieten her voice, she ignores me and/or increases her volume.</p>
<p>Sometimes I catch myself snapping, and instantly regret it. Not because I was wrong to set a limit — but because I did it in a way that disconnected us.</p>
<p>The bigger picture here is that she's disregulated and needs an adult ( AKA: me - even though I don't feel very adult in those times) to help regulate her.</p>
<p>Can you identify any situations like this for yourself? Someone is doing something that feels bad for you, but you don't want to hurt them or push them away?</p>
<p>I invite you to just notice what that feels like in your body for a moment before we continue. Does your chest tighten? Do you notice your jaw clench or your breath go shallow?</p>
<p>Now, notice what your typical response would be to this situation and what would that feel like in your body.</p>
<ul>
<li>Maybe you justify away your needs so that you can stay in connection?</li>
<li>Maybe you crack and yell out &quot;stop it&quot;!</li>
<li>Maybe you abruptly exit the situation and run away?</li>
</ul>
<p>I know all three of those responses well — the placating, the yelling, and the retreating. None of them feel good afterward.</p>
<p>Whatever it is, I invite you to get really clear on how that feels in your body.</p>
<p>What if boundaries didn’t have to be walls, but bridges — ways to stay real and stay close at the same time?</p>
<p>Here's what that might sound like in real life.</p>
<h2>A Different Kind of Boundary Language</h2>
<p>Hey (Name). I really want to stay in connection with you, but I can't right now because (overwhelming behaviour or situation) is happening. If it continues I'm going to have to do (thing that protects you from the situation or behaviour)</p>
<p>For example:
&quot;Hey Aspen (My daughter), I really want to hang out with you, but it's too loud right now and it's hurting my head. If it stays this loud I'm going to have to leave the room or shut the door. What would you like to do?&quot;</p>
<p>What would you say in the situation you're imagining?</p>
<h2>How This Changes the Feel of Connection</h2>
<p>Can you sense the tone of caring? It's about maintaining connection... and it's also protective.</p>
<p>It also doesn't pretend you have no power in the situation. It states clearly what the outcome will be if the person keeps doing that thing.</p>
<p>It gives context to the other person. It lets them know the bigger picture - that you want to be connected.</p>
<p>Maybe the other person had no idea that what they were doing was irritating to you. This is a kind way of letting them know.</p>
<p>Maybe they did know - if that is the case they now know what's going to happen if that continues.</p>
<p>This approach is an integration of the needs of both parts of yourself. The part that desires connection and the part that desires self protection.</p>
<h2>An Invitation to Try It for Yourself</h2>
<p>The beautiful thing about this approach is that you don't have to wait for an overwhelming situation to practice it.</p>
<p>You could think of a small situation today where there's something that is mildy irritating and try the words on for size.</p>
<p>In essence</p>
<ol>
<li>Name that you want connection</li>
<li>Name what you would need for that to improve</li>
</ol>
<p>Heck, you don't even need to have anything irritating. It's actually informative and educational for other people to understand your internal experience regardless of the situation.</p>
<p>Give it a go and let me know how you got on.</p>

    ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
  
    
    <entry>
      <title>What We’re Really Searching for in Love (And How to Find It)</title>
      <link href="https://www.tomwilson.nz/posts/what-were-really-searching-for-in-love/"/>
      <updated>2025-11-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <id>https://www.tomwilson.nz/posts/what-were-really-searching-for-in-love/</id>
      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
      <p>Have you found yourself moving from one relationship to the next, hoping this time you’ll finally find your person — only to watch it unravel again?</p>
<p>You try so hard to make it work. You listen, you communicate, you give your best… yet somehow you never feel deeply seen or valued.</p>
<p>After a few rounds of this, it starts to feel like a pattern — one you can’t quite name or escape. You want to love and be loved, but something keeps slipping through your fingers.</p>
<p>Maybe you've heard advice about what it takes to have a loving relationship...</p>
<h2>The Advice You’ve Probably Heard</h2>
<ul>
<li>Develop better communication skills.</li>
<li>Love yourself first before anyone else can truly love you.</li>
<li>You have to find the &quot;right person&quot;.</li>
<li>Just keep working at it - relationships take work.</li>
</ul>
<p>While there is truth in each of those statements, perhaps there's something deeper and more fundamentally human here at play here.</p>
<p><strong>That something is attunement.</strong></p>
<h2>What Attunement Really Means</h2>
<p>Humans are like instruments. If you're playing the flute and I'm playing the violin we need to play in tune with each other to create harmony.</p>
<p>It's an act of both playing a sound and listening for the others' sound. If we are both playing and both listening, we can find the notes which combine together to create something that sounds beautiful.</p>
<p>Have you had that experience with a person where everything just seemed to click? You're vibing off each other, you feel like the other person really &quot;gets&quot; you and you feel intimately connected - at least for that moment in time.</p>
<p>This is what it's like to be attuned and resonating with someone.  It's alive and exhilarating and it feels deeply rejuvenating.</p>
<h2>The Hidden Skill We’re All Born With</h2>
<p>I believe that this is a powerful and innate part of being human. This ability we have as social animals to be able to connect with each other.</p>
<p>Imagine what it would be like to create this type of connection with your partner consciously. What would that do to your sense of intimacy, connection and trust? Do you think that if this was  normal, you would feel more valued, cared-for and loved?</p>
<p>My experience tells me that resonance is a skill that can be nurtured. And the amazing thing is - it's NATURAL to us. We are wired for this type of connection. It's normal and it's not even a matter of learning anything. It's more about putting down the things that are getting in the way of it.</p>
<h2>How Resonance Begins</h2>
<p><strong>First, simply having the intention to do so.</strong></p>
<p>I used to consider myself a socially awkward person. I thought I wasn't cut out for connection with humans. So when I first started &quot;trying to resonate&quot; with people, I thought it was going to be a difficult and long path of learning some obscure skills that more socially savvy people had.</p>
<p>I was wrong. Within the first moments of just having the intention to do this, I realised that I already knew a lot about it. The resonance began to build immediately. It was built somewhere into my DNA. And it's built into your DNA too. This is human stuff that I'm talking about.</p>
<p><strong>The second part is the art of presence.</strong></p>
<p>Presence is about noticing what is here right now and being with that. It's the absence of needing to change something, fight it or run away from it.</p>
<h2>A Resonant Moment at the beach</h2>
<p>I met a man the other day at the beach. He was about 60, nearly toothless and extraordinarily enthusiastic. He loved to smile and laugh in close proximity to my face. At first I noticed myself being a bit overwhelmed by his large energy. I recoiled. But as I got present and accepted what was right there, I began to soften. I began to find my groove with this man.</p>
<p>Can you notice what it would be like to just see things as they are, without having to attach any meaning or judgement, any push or pull to the experience.</p>
<p>I could have interpreted this man as obnoxious, or wild or a bit unhinged. But I could also just see it simply as this moment unfolding in front of me. When I did, i started to feel the delight that this man was evidently feeling. I began to come into resonance with him and we shared an enriching experience together.</p>
<h2>An Invitation to Practice</h2>
<p>My invitation to you is to practice this with people. It can be with anyone, anywhere.</p>
<p>Notice yourself and your inner experience. Notice what is coming up for you as this person stands in front of you. Notice any stories you might tell yourself about them, or about yourself. Just let it all be there.</p>
<p>And underneath it all, hold the quiet intention: <em>“I want to be in tune with this person.”</em></p>
<p>Can you see how relating in this way would positively impact the connections in your life?</p>
<p>Once presence, attunement and resonance is in place, everything else — communication, love, trust — naturally begins to fall into place.</p>
<h2>Remembering What Love Really Is</h2>
<p>Attunement isn’t a technique. It’s a remembering — of something ancient, human, and endlessly alive in you. When you slow down enough to feel it, love begins to sound different. It’s less about effort, more about listening. Less about finding the one, more about <em>being</em> one — with yourself, and with whoever stands before you.</p>

    ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
  
    
    <entry>
      <title>Worried About Your Body’s Asymmetry? Here’s What’s Really Going On</title>
      <link href="https://www.tomwilson.nz/posts/worried-about-your-bodys-asymmetry/"/>
      <updated>2025-11-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <id>https://www.tomwilson.nz/posts/worried-about-your-bodys-asymmetry/</id>
      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
      <p>Have you ever noticed one side of your body working harder than the other? It can be a strange moment — like when a client once told me they heard a different sound every time they took a step. That was how they realized something wasn’t quite balanced.</p>
<p>For some people this discovery can be upsetting. Maybe you already take the health of your body seriously and the discovery of an asymmetry feels like something is not quite as healthy as it could be.</p>
<p>Perhaps you've already tried to address it using the common advice of training both sides equally, or training the weaker side more - but realised it doesn't fix anything.</p>
<p>This can feel disempowering - like you don't have any control over the body you exist in.</p>
<h2>The Truth - Everyone is Asymmetrical</h2>
<p>I'm here to tell you that NOBODY escapes asymmetry. In all the people who I've laid hands on, I have found asymmetry in every single one of them. It's normal and natural.</p>
<h2>When Asymmetry Becomes a Problem</h2>
<p>However, some asymmetry can be problematic. If you're still here reading, this may be something you're concerned about. Some asymmetry can lead to chronic pain, tension and discomfort. Many people have a sore hip, shoulder or back on one side.</p>
<p>But how do you know whether it's causing problems? And how do you become more symmetrical? Is it even possible?</p>
<p>I believe I have some answers to the questions. And I hope that by sharing them I encourage you to relate to your body and its differences in a more informed and accepting way.</p>
<p>I also hope to empower you to realise that you do actually have the power to change your body.</p>
<p>But to answer those questions we first need to take a closer look at the way your body and brain work together.</p>
<h2>The Organization of Your Body</h2>
<p>Your nervous system continually monitors information about your body. It knows things like the...</p>
<ul>
<li>bent position of your elbow</li>
<li>pressure of your contact with the floor</li>
<li>temperature of the air on your skin.</li>
<li>inclination of your head</li>
<li>exact location of your shoulder blade</li>
</ul>
<p>There is a LOT of information coming in. Like A LOT!!!</p>
<p>It decides based on that feedback and based on your intentions, how to organize your body.</p>
<p>It's like someone who organizes their bedroom. They decide oh I want a mirror here and my bed here. I want to have my clothes here so that when I get up in the morning I can easily access them. Then I want to keep all my indoor plants out of the way on the window sills so that I don't trip over them when it's dark.</p>
<p>In a similar way, your brain decides oh, I want to go swimming. So when you're in the water it's thinking &quot;okay so my arm needs to bend and move forward and pull me through the water&quot;. where is my arm anyway? Oh yeah there it is. It's a little off from where I thought, so I'm going to add a little more force in this muscle here and that should get the arm back on track again.</p>
<p>It's organizing the force that your muscles produce in order to achieve the positions and movements that you need to get done what you want to get done. And it's trying to do this in the most efficient way possible.</p>
<p>In addition, your brain is monitoring the water temperature, the depth of water, the weather conditions, your perceived danger. And it will adjust things in your organization to suit these perceptions.</p>
<p>This is an astonishingly complex problem that makes the organization of my bedroom seem ridiculously simple (for some reason it doesn't feel this simple!)</p>
<h2>Escaping the Machine-Body Myth</h2>
<p>Why is this frame of understanding important? Because a common cultural view is that of the machine-body metaphor. It’s the worldview that sees the body as something to maintain, fuel, fix, or upgrade. The perspective that we are just a bunch of parts.</p>
<p>It's the reason we have knee doctors and foot doctors and hand specialists and teeth specialists. It's the reason we get hip replacements and knee replacements and breast implants.</p>
<p>This world-view ignores or downplays the fact that we are biological, aware, living organisms.</p>
<p>It ignores the fact that all of your movement and your posture is centrally governed by your nervous system.</p>
<p>If you're coming from the worldview of the body-as-machine. The natural response to asymmetry is to just train the part more. Or move the part differently.</p>
<p>But my experience of this, is that it just doesn't stick.</p>
<p>However, when you're viewing this problem through the (more truthful) lens that we are living, learning organic beings. It becomes more obvious that this problem must be approached at the level of central government. The level of the nervous system.</p>
<h2>If You’ve Tried and Nothing’s Worked...</h2>
<p>So if you're finding yourself...</p>
<ul>
<li>limping, or</li>
<li>your left shoulder is stuck, or</li>
<li>one of your arms swings a lot when you walk while the other is almost stationary</li>
</ul>
<p>..and you don't know what to do about it. Or if you've been doing some training and it's not making a difference.</p>
<p>First of all know that this is not your fault. It's not some personal failing on your part. This way of looking at the body and brain is extremely uncommon. Probably everything you've heard your entire life is more based on this body-as-machine metaphor. At least it was for me.</p>
<p>Secondly, know that this is actually really great news. It it fantastic news actually. Because you have a nervous system that is astonishingly smart — seriously, it’s been fine-tuning your every move since before you could walk. This means that when you learn how to work with it properly, changes can happen fast.</p>
<h2>Some Asymmetry Is Beautifully Normal</h2>
<p>Additionally, I mentioned earlier that not all asymmetry is problematic.</p>
<p>One simple example is that our left lung is smaller than our right. For everyone. The heart sits on the left size of the chest and so there's less room for a lung. natures solution? Smaller left lung.</p>
<p>This changes the shape of our breathing in the left side of our ribcage. This is just one small example of something that isn't balanced.</p>
<p>Another is the people are naturally born right or left handed. We all know this one. We have asymmetric preferences and so it makes sense we use our bodies in ways that aren't balanced.</p>
<p>Hopefully that can also break down the idea that any asymmetry is bad. Because it isn't.</p>
<h2>When the Pattern Gets Stuck</h2>
<p>But some asymmetry is problematic.</p>
<p>An injury which caused you to limp for a period while it healed but then the limp never stopped, is likely a problematic asymmetry.</p>
<p>Maybe you're missing a leg. Or you have scoliosis.</p>
<p>These can be problematic. But it's also possible to learn how to move more optimally regardless of whether your asymmetry is neurological in origin (like the lingering limp), or structural in origin. Like a scoliosis.</p>
<h2>The Key: Re-educating the Nervous System</h2>
<p>Regardless of the state of your body and mind, the only way to resolve the resolveable asymmetries is by exploring it with your senses and upgrading your sensory motor maps.</p>
<p>This process does 2 things.</p>
<ol>
<li>It gives your nervous system information about yourself.</li>
<li>Your nervous system uses that information to re-organize.</li>
</ol>
<p>Through the process of sensory and movement exploration, you change.</p>
<p>It's like &quot;diagnosis&quot; and &quot;repair&quot; are both the same step.</p>
<h2>Let Your Brain Do Its Job</h2>
<p>This is like getting clear on household responsibilities. Maybe you're the one who empties the bins, takes out the recycling and does the shopping. Maybe your partner cooks the dinner and walks the dog.</p>
<p>If you start interfering with the process of cooking the dinner, you cause problems. It's not your job. If you neglect to do your job, there wont be ingredients for dinner.</p>
<p>In the same way, if you start trying to fix your asymmetry directly, you won't be able to. It's not your job.</p>
<p>If you neglect to feed your brain good quality ingredients, it won't be able to update your asymmetry.</p>
<p>To clarify:</p>
<p>Your job is to feed your brain good quality sensory information.</p>
<p>Your brains job is to reorganize based on that information.</p>
<p>So if you've been struggling with asymmetries which you think are problematic. The approach is about getting better at your job.</p>
<p>Learning how to feed great information into your system is what moves the needle.</p>
<h2>Where Feldenkrais Comes In</h2>
<p>How does someone do that? Glad you asked. This is where feldenkrais enters the picture. Feldenkrais is a methodology which does just that. It is a practice that gradually updates and improves your brains representation of the body.</p>
<p>It deepens coordination, movement efficiency and often will balance out asymmetry's - but only if your nervous system judges that the new &quot;organization&quot; is a better option...which in many cases it is.</p>
<p>If you’d like to experience how this works in your own body, reach out and we can explore what kind of movement practice might help you sense and shift your own patterns.</p>

    ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
  
    
    <entry>
      <title>Why Sitting at a Computer Doesn’t Have to Ruin Your Posture</title>
      <link href="https://www.tomwilson.nz/posts/sitting-at-computer-doesnt-have-to-ruin-posture/"/>
      <updated>2025-11-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <id>https://www.tomwilson.nz/posts/sitting-at-computer-doesnt-have-to-ruin-posture/</id>
      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
      <p>Do you ever catch yourself - maybe in a mirror or just through felt sense - with your shoulders rounded forward?</p>
<p>Or notice your head is jutted forward, as though you were looking closely at a computer screen, even when you're out walking?</p>
<p>What about now?</p>
<p>How does your posture feel in this moment? Feel the weight of your head resting on your spine. No need to correct anything - just notice how your body meets this moment.</p>
<p>What do you notice that surprises you?</p>
<h2>I used to struggle with my posture</h2>
<p>When I was a kid I used to play computer games and I did a stint for a couple of years of computer programming in my early 20's. During this period, despite being very physically active, my posture was less than ideal.</p>
<p>I would slouch, I would hold my head forwards and I would have a lot of tension in my upper back after spending long hours at the computer.</p>
<p>For years I thought posture was something you had to fix — that I’d somehow done it wrong. No matter how hard I tried, the tension always came back.</p>
<p>That experience combined with what I'd heard from society was that computers give you bad posture. I believed it.</p>
<h2>The deeper truth about computer posture</h2>
<p>But what I came to discover through my Feldenkrais training is that it's not actually the computer use which is a problem. It's the way you use yourSELF while you're on the computer that makes a difference.</p>
<p>I still use my computer daily, but now I have a different approach which allows me to have good posture while I'm using it. I also don't &quot;pay for it later&quot; like I used to if I've been on there for a long time.</p>
<p>It's simply a case of learning how to use your body differently.</p>
<h2>Your Posture Comes From The Freedom Or Restriction Of Movement In Your Spine</h2>
<p>Bad posture generally comes from muscles being stuck &quot;on&quot;. That is, they have contracted, and they are not de-contracting.</p>
<p>This is most common in the extensor muscles - the muscles that run down your back and help it arch and stay upright.</p>
<p>When people have back muscles that are free, their posture looks beautiful. Consider a 2 year old. Their posture is perfect and their back muscles are responsive.</p>
<p>When people have habitual contraction in their back, their posture gets messed up. It prevents the little micro movements that healthy vertebrae should have.</p>
<h2>A Healthy Spine Can Flow</h2>
<p>Each vertebra is meant to whisper to the next — passing movement along the way a wave moves through water. When some get quiet, others start shouting.</p>
<p>I invite you to check in with the free movement of your spine right now.</p>
<p>What happens if you exaggerate your slouch for a moment — and then very slowly let it go? Notice which parts of your spine move first, and which hold back.</p>
<p>When you move your spine, can you feel which parts join in easily and which parts seem shy? Try a slow arch, a slow round, maybe even a gentle twist.</p>
<p>Most people notice that some parts are eager while others hesitate — that’s totally normal. Those hesitations are simply the places where your nervous system has learned to “hold on.”</p>
<p>Those hesitations you feel are your nervous system doing what it’s practiced most often. Your spine has developed habits based on those movements it has practiced most.</p>
<h2>Your Spinal Movement is Controlled by Your Habits</h2>
<p>Every adult I know carries some pattern of contraction — it’s just how the nervous system learns to keep us safe. These are the ways that we have learned to use our bodies and they have become so deeply embedded that we don't even think about them anymore. These are our HABITS of contraction.</p>
<p>These habits are unique to each person. They're like a fingerprint.</p>
<p>The way they differ from fingerprints though, is that it's possible to change your muscular habits.</p>
<h2>How Habits are Changed</h2>
<p>It's just like the way you have a habit of brushing your teeth. You do know you always brush the same way right?</p>
<p>If you're like most people, you probably do. You probably start with the same tooth, follow the same sequence and finish in the same way.</p>
<p>If you wanted to change this habit (which can be kinda fun because it feels strange). You first have to notice the way you currently do it. Maybe you do the top right molars first and then move around anti-clockwise to the other teeth.</p>
<p>Then you would have to try out a new sequence. Maybe you choose to brush the bottom teeth first. Then moving up to the top.</p>
<p>You could explore some different sequences and see what feels nicest to you.</p>
<p>Here's the interesting part - if your nervous system likes the new way of brushing your teeth because it's more comfortable or uses less effort, it will adopt the new habit.</p>
<p>You may have to practice it a little in case the old pattern re-asserts it's dominance.</p>
<p>But in essence, this is habit change.</p>
<h2>You Can Change the Movement Habits of Your Back</h2>
<p>The process is no different for changing the habitual movements of your back muscles.</p>
<p>In the same way you brush your teeth in sequence, you’ve got a habitual ‘sequence’ in how your back muscles fire as you stand, sit, or look at a screen.</p>
<p>Once you see that sequence clearly, you can start to explore it and then play with some new patterns.</p>
<p>This is really what posture change is about. It's not about pulling your head back and trying to &quot;fix it&quot;.</p>
<p>When you start to feel how your posture responds to attention instead of effort, you begin to move from fixing to sensing — and that’s where real change begins.</p>
<h2>Play With Your Habit</h2>
<p>In invite you to take a moment now to sense what this process of habit change is like. You can just lower your head a small amount - maybe only 10 or 20% as far as you could go.</p>
<p>Before you move, just notice where your attention rests. Feel the contact your body makes with the chair or the ground. Let yourself arrive.</p>
<p>Slowly move back and forth between being upright and with your head curled forward. As you do this, see if you can identify the way your spine habitually moves... You might ask yourself, &quot;Where is the very first vertebrae that moves?&quot; and then &quot;Whats the sequence of vertebrae that follow?&quot;</p>
<p>Then, when you’re ready, you might experiment with other ways. Perhaps you could initiate the bend from a little further down your spine. Play with it and let some other vertebrae be involved. Let ease be your guide. Could you do this so gently that it becomes a search for joy through your movement?</p>
<p>That's right. Feel the way you can find easy breathing and simplicity as you move back and forth - each time deepening into more softness.</p>
<p>Once your curiosity has run its course, you can bring the movements to a stop. Now there's an opportunity to spend a moment sensing your posture. Is there something softer about it? More gentle? Do you like this way of using yourSELF?</p>
<p>Take a moment to simply feel yourself sitting here now — breathing, alive, supported.<br>
Notice what’s different, even if it’s subtle.<br>
That’s your nervous system learning — through you.</p>
<p>Imagine if you were able to amplify this quality of ease and softness in your posture. How would this change the way you show up while using a computer? Or in other areas of life? How would you see yourself as your move through your life with a softer, more effortless version of posture?</p>

    ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
  
</feed>